Guide to the Robert Staughton Lynd papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Robert Staughton Lynd papers,
1933-1945
[Bulk Dates: 1933-1935].
Lynd, Robert Staughton, 1892-1970.
.42 linear ft. (1 Document box)
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library New York, NY. 10027
MS#0812
4079056
Robert Staughton Lynd’s papers consist primarily of correspondence, meetings’ minutes, proposals, studies, and reports regarding the National Recovery Administration and the Consumers Advisory Board. In addition, there are newspaper and magazine clippings about consumer interests during the early 1930s.
Biographical Note
Robert Staughton Lynd was born on September 26, 1892 in New Albany, Indiana. He was a professor of sociology at Columbia University for thirty years (1931-1961.) He married Helen Merrell in September, 1922. They had two children, a son, Staughton, in 1929, and a daughter, Andrea, in 1934.
Lynd is best known for the book, Middletown: A Study in Contemporary American Culture, that he and his wife wrote. The book was based on a landmark study of a typical American community in 1929 from a cultural anthropological standpoint. It was one of the first sociological analyses done in the country of a modern, urban community. The book proved to be a bestseller and was noted for its scientific perspective. Lynd and his wife followed up with a sequel titled, Middletown in Transition in 1937 by returning to the same community to observe the effects of the Great Depression on its people. Known as the Middletown studies, these analyses are still used and referred to by American sociologists.
Lynd died on November 1, 1970 in Warren, CT, at the age of seventy-eight.
Scope and Content
Lynd's papers primarily consist of letters, memos, proposals, meetings' minutes, studies, newspaper and magazine clippings, releases, and legal documents pertaining to the National Recovery Administration regulation and the Consumer Advisory Board during the early 1930s.
In addition, the collection contains policies and reports on educational reform in Great Britain and of the National Maritime Union.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in four series
Series I: Correspondence, 1933-1937
Series II: Administrative Files, 1933-1935
Series III: Legal Documents, 1933-1934
Series IV: Educational Files, 1942-1943
Subjects
Columbia University--Faculty.; United States.--National Recovery Administration.--Consumers' Advisory Board.; National Maritime Union of America.; Lynd, Robert Staughton, 1892-1970,--Middletown.; Lynd, Helen Merrell, 1896-1982.; United States--Economic conditions--1918-1945.; Working class--Education--United States.; Working class--Education--Great Britain.; College teachers.; Sociologists.
Access Restrictions
This collection is located off-site. You will need to request this material at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
This collection has no restrictions.
Acquisition
1961 M-61 Lynd, Robert S. Gift
Selected Related Material--At Other Repositories
Robert and Helen Lynd Family Papers, Staughton Lynd Collection Kent State University
Lynd Correspondence and Papers, 1922-1982, Ball State University Libraries
Middletown Studies Collection and Digital Archive Ball State University
- Series I: Correspondence, 1933-1937
  This series contains letters from the National Recovery Administration and memos from the Consumer Advisory Board.
  - Letters from National Recovery Administration, 1933-1935 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letters from Consumer Agencies and Colleagues, 1933-1937 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Consumer Advisory Board Memos, 1933-1935 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Series II: Administrative Files, 1933-1935
  In this series, the papers are comprised of minutes, studies, proposals, reports, newspaper and magazine clippings and press releases regarding the Consumer Advisory Board.
  - Consumer Advisory Board Meetings' Minutes, 1933-1935 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Consumer Advisory Board Studies, 1933-1935 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Consumer Advisory Board Proposals, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - National Recovery Administration Releases, 1933-1935 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Consumer Advisory Board Presentations, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - County Consumers Councils Reports, 1934 June-December (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Newspaper and Magazine Clippings, 1933-1935 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Series III: Legal Documents, 1933-1934
  This series consists of National Industrial Recovery Act regulations and amendments.
  - National Industrial Recovery Act Regulations and Amendments, 1933-1934 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Series IV: Educational Files, 1942-1943
  These files contain educational reform policies and social welfare reports in Great Britain as well as the National Maritime Union Training School policies.
  - British Educational Reform Policies, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Social Welfare Reports in Great Britain, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - American Labor Education Study, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - National Maritime Union Training School Policies, 1944-1945 (Box 1, Folder 15)